Hi, everyone.
Welcome to CS 25
Transformers United V2.
This was a course that
was held at Stanford
in the winter of 2023.
This course is not
about robots that
can transform into cars as
this picture might suggest.
Rather, it's about
deep learning models
that have taken
the world by storm
and have revolutionized
the field of AI and others.
Starting from natural
language processing,
transformers have
been applied all over,
computer vision, reinforcement
learning, biology, robotics,
et cetera.
We have an exciting set
of videos lined up for you
with some truly fascinating
speakers, talks, presenting
how they're applying
transformers
to the research in
different fields and areas.
We hope you'll enjoy and
learn from these videos.
So without any further
ado, let's get started.
This is a purely
introductory lecture.
And we'll go into the building
blocks of transformers.
So first, let's start with
introducing the instructors.
So for me, I'm currently on a
temporary deferral from the PhD
program, and I'm leading AI at a
robotics startup, Collaborative
Robotics, that are working on
some general purpose robots,
somewhat like [INAUDIBLE].
And I'm very passionate about
robotics and building FSG
learning algorithms.
My research interests are
in reinforcement learning,
computer vision, and
remodeling, and I
have a bunch of
publications in robotics,
autonomous driving,
and other areas.
My undergrad was at Cornell.
If someone is from Cornell,
so nice to [INAUDIBLE]..
So I'm Stephen, currently
a first-year CS PhD here.
Previously did my master's at
CMU and undergrad at Waterloo.
I'm mainly into NLP research,
anything involving language
and text, but more
recently, I've
been getting more into computer
vision as well as [INAUDIBLE]
And just some stuff I do
for fun, a lot of music
stuff, mainly piano.
Some self-promo of what I post
a lot on my Insta, YouTube,
and TikTok, so if you
guys want to check it out.
My friends and I are also
starting a Stanford piano club,
so if anybody's interested,
feel free to email
or DM me for details.
Other than that, martial arts,
bodybuilding, and huge fan
of k-dramas, anime,
and occasional gamer.
[LAUGHS]
OK, cool.
Yeah, so my name is Rylan.
Instead of talking
about myself, I just
want to very briefly
say that I'm super
excited to take this class.
I took it the last time--
sorry-- to teach this.
Excuse me.
I took it the last
time I was offered.
I had a bunch of fun.
I thought we brought in a
really great group of speakers
last time.
I'm super excited
for this offering.
And yeah, I'm thankful
that you're all here,
and I'm looking forward to a
really fun quarter together.
Thank you.
Yeah, so fun fact, Rylan was
the most outspoken student
last year.
And so if someone wants to
become an instructor next year,
you know what to do.
[LAUGHTER]
OK, cool.
Let's see.
OK, I think we
have a few minutes.
So what we hope you will learn
in this class is, first of all,
how do transformers
work, how they
are being applied,
just beyond NLP,
and nowadays, like they
are pretty [INAUDIBLE]
them everywhere in
AI machine learning.
And what are some new and
interesting directions
of research in these topics.
Cool, so this class is
just an introductory.
So we're just talking about
the basics of transformers,
introducing them, talking about
the self-attention mechanism
on which they're founded.
And we'll do a deep dive
more on models like BERT
to GPT, stuff like that.
So with that, happy
to get started.
OK, so let me start with
presenting the attention
timeline.
Attention all started
with this one paper.
[INAUDIBLE] by
Vaswani et al in 2017.
That was the beginning
of transformers.
Before that, we had
the prehistoric error,
where we had models
like RNM, LSDMs,
and simple attention
mechanisms that didn't work
or [INAUDIBLE].
Starting 2017, we saw this
explosion of transformers
into NLP, where people started
using it for everything.
I even heard this
quote from Google.
It's like our performance
increased every time
we [INAUDIBLE]
[CHUCKLES]
For the [INAUDIBLE]
after 2018 to 2020,
we saw this explosion
of transformers
into other fields like vision,
a bunch of other stuff,
and like biology as a whole.
And in last year,
2021 was the start
of the generative era, where we
got a lot of genetic modeling,
started models like
Codex, GPT, DALL-E,
stable diffusions,
or a lot of things
happening in genetic modeling.
And we started scaling up in AI.
And now, the present.
So this is 2022 and
the startup in '23.
And now we have models
like ChatGPT, Whisperer,
a bunch of others.
And we're scaling onwards
without splitting up,
so that's great.
So that's the future.
So going more into this,
so once there were RNNs.
So we had Seq2Seq
models, LSTMs, GRU.
What worked there was that they
were good at encoding history,
but what did not work was they
didn't encode long sequences
and they were very bad
at encoding context.
So consider this example.
Consider trying to predict
the last word in the text,
"I grew up in France,
dot, dot, dot.
I speak fluent Dutch."
Here, you need to understand
the context for it
to predict French, and
attention mechanism
is very good at that, whereas
if they're just using LSDMs,
it doesn't here work that well.
Another thing transformers
are good at is,
more based on content, is
also context prediction
is like finding attention maps.
If I have something
like a word like it,
what noun does it correlate to.
And we can give a
property attention
on one of the
possible activations.
And this works better
than existing mechanisms.
OK, so where we were in 2021,
we were on the verge of takeoff.
We were starting to realize
the potential of transformers
in different fields.
We solved a lot of
long sequence problems
like protein folding,
AlphaFold, offline RL.
We started to see few-shots,
zero-shot generalization.
We saw multimodal
tasks and applications
like generating
images from language.
So that was DALL-E. And
it feels like [INAUDIBLE]..
And this was also a
talk on transformers
that you can watch on YouTube.
Yeah, cool.
And this is where we were
going from 2021 to 2022,
which is we have gone from
the version of [INAUDIBLE]
And now, we are seeing
unique applications
in audio generation,
art, music, storytelling.
We are starting to see
these new capabilities
like commonsense,
logical reasoning,
mathematical reasoning.
We are also able to now
get human enlightenment
and interaction.
They're able to use
reinforcement learning
and human feedback.
That's how ChatGPT is trained
to perform really good.
We have a lot of
mechanisms for controlling
toxicity bias and ethics now.
And there are a
lot of also, a lot
of developments in other
areas like diffusion models.
Cool.
So the future is a
spaceship, and we are all
excited about it.
And there's a lot
of more applications
that we can enable,
and it'll be great
if you can see
transformers also up there.
One big example is video
understanding and generation.
That is something that
everyone is interested in,
and I'm hoping we'll
see a lot of models
in this area this year,
also, finance, business.
I'll be very excited to
see GPT author a novel,
but we need to solve very
long sequence modeling.
And most transformer
models are still
limited to 4,000 tokens
or something like that.
So we need to make them
generalize much more
better on long sequences.
We also want to have
generalized agents
that can do a lot of multitask,
a multi-input predictions
like Gato.
And so I think we will
see more of that, too.
And finally, we also want
domain specific models.
So you might want
a GPT model, let's
put it like maybe your health.
So that could be like
a DoctorGPT model.
You might have a
LawyerGPT model that's
trained on only law data.
So currently, we have GPT models
that are trained on everything.
But we might start to see
more niche models that
are good at one task.
And we could have a
mixture of experts,
so it's like, you
can think this is a--
how you'd normally
consult an expert,
you'll have expert AI models.
And you can go to a different AI
model for your different needs.
There are still a lot
of missing ingredients
to make this all successful.
The first of all
is external memory.
We are already starting to
see this with the models
like ChatGPT, where the
inflections are short-lived.
There's no long-term
memory, and they
don't have ability
to remember or store
conversations for long-term.
And this is something
you want to fix.
Second is reducing the
computation complexity.
So attention mechanism is
quadratic over the sequence
length, which is slow.
And we want to reduce
it and make it faster.
Another thing we
want to do is we
want to enhance the
controllability of these models
like a lot of these
models can be stochastic.
And we want to be able to
control what sort of outputs
we get from them.
And you might have
experienced the ChatGPT,
if you just refresh, you get
different output each time.
But you might want to have
a mechanism that controls
what sort of things you get.
And finally, we want to align
our state of art language
models with how the
human brain works.
And we are seeing the
surge, but we still
need more research on seeing
how they can make more informed.
Thank you.
Great, hi.
Yes, I'm excited to be here.
I live very nearby, so I got
the invites to come to class.
And I was like, OK,
I'll just walk over.
But then I spent like
10 hours on the slides,
so it wasn't as simple.
So yeah, I'm going to
talk about transformers.
I'm going to skip the
first two over there.
I'm not going to
talk about those.
We'll talk about that one
just to simplify the lecture
since we don't have time.
OK, so I wanted to provide
a little bit of context
on why does this transformers
class even exist.
So a little bit of
historical context.
I feel like Bilbo over there.
I joined like telling
you guys about this.
I don't know if you guys
saw Lord of the Rings.
And basically, I joined AI in
roughly 2012, the full course,
so maybe a decade ago.
And back then, you
wouldn't even say
that you joined AI by the way.
That was like a dirty word.
Now, it's OK to talk
about, but back then, it
was not even deep learning.
It was machine learning.
That was the term we would
use if you were serious.
But now, now, AI is
OK to use, I think.
So basically, do
you even realize
how lucky you are
potentially entering
this area in roughly 2023?
So back then, in 2011 or so
when I was working specifically
on computer vision, your
pipeline's looked like this.
So you wanted to
classify some images,
you would go to a paper, and I
think this is representative.
You would have three pages
in the paper describing
all kinds of a zoo,
of kitchen sink,
of different kinds of
features, descriptors.
And you would go
to a poster session
and in computer
vision conference,
and everyone would have their
favorite feature descriptor
that they're proposing.
And it's totally
ridiculous, and you
would take notes on which
one you should incorporate
into your pipeline because
you would extract all of them,
and then you would
put an SVM on top.
So that's what you would do.
So there's two pages.
Make sure you get your
[? Spar ?] SIFT histograms,
your SSIMs, your color
histograms, textiles,
tiny images.
And don't forget the
geometry specific histograms.
All of them have basically
complicated code by themselves.
So you're collecting code from
everywhere and running it,
and it was a total nightmare.
So on top of that,
it also didn't work.
[LAUGHTER]
So this would be, I think,
it represents the prediction
from that time.
You would just get predictions
like this once in a while,
and you'd be like, you
just shrug your shoulders
like that just happens
once in a while.
Today, you would be
looking for a bug.
And worse than that,
every single chunk of AI
had their own completely
separate vocabulary
that they work with.
So if you go to NLP
papers, those papers
would be completely different.
So you're reading the NLP
paper, and you're like,
what is this part
of speech tagging,
morphological analysis,
and tactic parsing,
co-reference resolution?
What is MPBTKJ?
And you're confused.
So the vocabulary and everything
was completely different.
And you couldn't
read papers, I would
say, across different areas.
So now, that
changed a little bit
starting 2012 when Al Krizhevsky
and colleagues basically
demonstrated that if you
scale a large neural network
on large data set, you can
get very strong performance.
And so up till then, there was
a lot of focus on algorithms.
But this showed that actually
neural nets scale very well.
So you need to now worry
about compute and data,
and you can scale it up.
It works pretty well.
And then that recipe
actually did copy paste
across many areas of AI.
So we start to see neural
networks pop up everywhere
since 2012.
So we saw them in computer
vision, and NLP, and speech,
and translation in RL and so on.
So everyone started to use
the same kind of modeling
toolkit, modeling framework.
And now when you go to NLP, and
you start reading papers there,
in machine translation,
for example,
this is a sequence
to sequence paper
which we'll come
back to in a bit.
You start to read those
papers, and you're like, OK,
I can recognize these words.
Like there's a neural network.
There's some parameters.
There's an optimizer, and
it starts to read things
that you know of.
So that decreased tremendously
the barrier to entry
across the different areas.
And then, I think,
the big deal is
that when the transformer
came out in 2017,
it's not even that just the tool
kits and the neural networks
were similar-- there's that
literally the architectures
converged to like one
architecture that you
copy paste across
everything seemingly.
So this was kind of an
unassuming machine translation
paper at the time, proposing
to transformer architecture.
But what we found since then
is that you can just basically
copy paste this architecture
and use it everywhere.
And what's changing is
the details of the data,
and the chunking of the
data, and how you feed it in.
And that's a
caricature, but it's
kind of like a correct
first order statement.
And so now, papers are
even more similar looking
because everyone's
just using transformer.
And so this convergence
was remarkable to watch
and unfolded over
the last decade.
And it's pretty crazy to me.
What I find
interesting is I think
this is some kind of a hint
that we're maybe converging
to something that maybe
the brain is doing
because the brain is very
homogeneous and uniform
across the entire
sheet of your cortex.
And OK, maybe some of
the details are changing,
but those feel like
hyperparameters
like a transformer.
But your auditory cortex
and your visual cortex
and everything else
looks very similar.
And so maybe we're
converging to some kind
of a uniform powerful
learning algorithm here.
Something like that, I think,
is interesting and exciting.
OK, so I want to talk about
where the transformer came
from briefly, historically.
So I want to start in 2003.
I like this paper quite a bit.
It was the first popular
application of neural networks
to the problem of
language modeling,
so predicting in this
case, the next word
in the sequence, which
allows you to build
generative models over text.
And in this case, they were
using multi-layer perceptron,
so very simple neural net.
The neural nets took three words
and predicted the probability
distribution for the
fourth word in a sequence.
So this was well and
good at this point.
Now, over time, people
started to apply this
to machine translation.
So that brings us to
sequence to sequence paper
from 2014 that was
pretty influential,
and the big problem
here was OK, we
don't just want to take three
words and predict the fourth.
We want to predict how to
go from an English sentence
to a French sentence.
And the key problem
was OK, you can
have arbitrary number of words
in English and arbitrary number
of words in French,
so how do you
get an architecture
that can process
this variably sized input?
And so here they used a
LSDM, and there's basically
two chunks of this, which are
covered by the slack, by this.
But basically have an
encoder LSDM on the left,
and it just consumes
one word at a time
and builds up a context
of what it has read.
And then that acts as
a conditioning vector
to the decoder RNN or LSDM.
That basically
goes chonk, chonk,
chonk for the next
word in a sequence,
translating the English to
French or something like that.
Now, the big problem with
this, that people identified,
I think, very quickly
and tried to resolve
is that there's what's called
this encoder bottleneck.
So this entire English sentence
that we are trying to condition
on is packed into
a single vector
that goes from the
encoder to the decoder.
And so this is just
too much information
to potentially maintain
in a single vector,
and that didn't seem correct.
And so people who are
looking around for ways
to alleviate the attention of
the encoder bottleneck as it
was called at the time.
And so that brings
us to this paper,
Neural Machine Translation
by Jointly Learning
to Align and Translate.
And here, just quoting from
the abstract, "in this paper,
we conjectured that the use
of a fixed length vector
is a bottleneck in
improving the performance
of the basic
encoder-decoder architecture
and propose to extend
this by allowing
the model to
automatically soft search
for parts of the source sentence
that are relevant to predicting
a target word without
having to form
these parts or hard
segments exclusively."
So this was a way to look
back to the words that
are coming from the encoder.
And it was achieved
using this soft search.
So as you are
decoding in the words
here, while you
are decoding them,
you are allowed to
look back at the words
at the encoder via this soft
attention mechanism proposed
in this paper.
And so this paper, I think,
is the first time that I saw,
basically, attention.
So your context vector
that comes from the encoder
is a weighted sum
of the hidden states
of the words in the encoding.
And then the weights
of this sum come
from a softmax that is based
on these compatibilities
between the current
state as you're decoding
and the hidden states
generated by the encoder.
And so this is the first
time that really you
start to look at it, and this
is the current modern equations
of the attention.
And I think this was the
first paper that I saw it in.
It's the first time
that there's a word
attention used, as far as I
know, to call this mechanism.
So I actually tried to dig
into the details of the history
of the attention.
So the first author
here, Dzmitry, I
had an email
correspondence with him,
and I basically
sent him an email.
I'm like, Dzmitry, this
is really interesting.
Just rumors have taken over.
Where did you come up
with the soft attention
mechanism that ends up being
the heart of the transformer?
And to my surprise, he wrote me
back this massive email, which
was really fascinating.
So this is an excerpt
from that email.
So basically, he talks about
how he was looking for a way
to avoid this bottleneck
between the encoder and decoder.
He had some ideas
about cursors that
traverse the sequences
that didn't quite work out.
And then here, "so one
day, I had this thought
that it would be nice
to enable the decoder
RNN to learn to search where
to put the cursor in the source
sequence.
This was sort of inspired
by translation exercises
that learning English in
my middle school involved.
Your gaze shifts back and forth
between source and target,
sequence as you translate."
So literally, I thought that
this was kind of interesting,
that he's not a native
English speaker,
and here, that gave him an edge
in this machine translation
that led to attention and
then led to transformer.
So that's really fascinating.
"I expressed a soft
search a softmax
and then weighted averaging
of the [INAUDIBLE] states.
And basically, to
my great excitement,
this worked from
the very first try."
So really, I think,
interesting piece of history.
And as it later turned out
that the name of RNN search
was kind of lame, so the
better name attention came
from Yoshua on one
of the final passes
as they went over the paper.
So maybe Attention
is All You Need
would have been called RNN
Search is All You Need,
but we have Yoshua
Bengio to thank
for a little bit of
better name, I would say.
So apparently,
that's the history
of this, which I
thought was interesting.
OK, so that brings us to
2017, which is Attention
is All You Need.
So this attention
component, which
in Dzmitry's paper was
just one small segment,
and there's all this
bidirectional RNN, RNN
and decoder, and this Attention
All You Need paper is saying,
OK, you can actually
delete everything.
What's making this
work very well
is just attention by itself.
And so delete everything,
keep attention.
And then what's remarkable about
this paper actually is usually,
you see papers that
are very incremental.
They add one thing, and
they show that it's better.
But I feel like
Attention is All You
Need was like a mix of multiple
things at the same time.
They were combined
in a very unique way,
and then also achieve a
very good local minimum
in the architecture space.
And so to me, this is
really a landmark paper
that is quite
remarkable and, I think,
had quite a lot of
work behind the scenes.
So delete all the RNN,
just keep attention.
Because attention
operates over sets--
and I'm going to go
to this in a second--
you now need to positionally
encode your inputs
because attention doesn't have
the notion of space by itself.
I have to be very careful.
They adopted this
residual network structure
from resonance.
They interspersed attention
with multi-layer perceptrons.
They used layer norms, which
came from a different paper.
They introduced the concept
of multiple heads of attention
that were applied in parallel.
And they gave us, I think,
like a fairly good set
of hyperparameters that
to this day are used.
So the expansion factor in the
multi-layer perceptron goes up
by 4X--
and we'll go into
a bit more detail--
and this 4X has stuck around.
And I believe there's
a number of papers
that try to play with all
kinds of little details
of the transformer, and nothing
sticks because this is actually
quite good.
The only thing to my
knowledge that didn't stick
was this reshuffling
of the layer norms
to go into the prenorm
version where here you
see the layer norms are after
the multiheaded attention feed
forward.
They just put them
before instead.
So just reshuffling of
layer norms, but otherwise,
the TPTs and everything else
that you're seeing today
is basically the 2017
architecture from 5 years ago.
And even though everyone
is working on it,
it's been proven
remarkably resilient,
which I think is
real interesting.
There are innovations
that, I think,
have been adopted also
in positional encoding.
It's more common to use
different rotary and relative
positional encoding and so on.
So I think there have been
changes, but for the most part,
it's proven very resilient.
So really quite an
interesting paper.
Now, I wanted to go into
the attention mechanism.
And I think, the way I interpret
it is not similar to the ways
that I've seen it
presented before.
So let me try a different
way of how I see it.
Basically, to me, attention is
kind of like the communication
phase of the transformer,
and the transformer
interweaves two phases of the
communication phase, which
is the multi-headed
attention, and the computation
stage, which is this
multilayered perceptron
or [INAUDIBLE].
So in the communication
phase, it's
really just a data
dependent message
passing on directed graphs.
And you can think of it
as OK, forget everything
with machine
translation, everything.
Let's just-- we have
directed graphs.
At each node, you
are storing a vector.
And then let me talk now
about the communication
phase of how these
vectors talk to each other
and this directed graph.
And then the compute
phase later is just
a multi-perceptron, which then
basically acts on every node
individually.
But how do these nodes
talk to each other
in this directed graph?
So I wrote like
some simple Python--
I wrote this in Python
basically to create
one round of communication
of using attention
as the message passing scheme.
So here, a node has this
private data vector,
as you can think of it
as private information
to this node.
And then it can also emit a
key, a query, and a value.
And simply, that's done
by linear transformation
from this node.
So the key is what are
the things that I am--
sorry.
The query is what are the
things that I'm looking for?
The key is what other
the things that I have?
And the value is what are the
things that I will communicate?
And so then when you
have your graph that's
made up of nodes in some
random edges, when you actually
have these nodes communicating,
what's happening is
you loop over all the
nodes individually
in some random order,
and you're at some node,
and you get the
query vector q, which
is, I'm a node in
some graph, and this
is what I'm looking for.
And so that's just achieved
via this linear transformation
here.
And then we look at all the
inputs that point to this node,
and then they broadcast what
are the things that I have,
which is their keys.
So they broadcast the keys.
I have the query, then those
interact by dot product
to get scores.
So basically, simply
by doing dot product,
you get some
unnormalized weighting
of the interestingness of all
of the information in the nodes
that point to me and to
the things I'm looking for.
And then when you normalize
that with softmax,
so it just sums to
1, you basically just
end up using those scores, which
now sum to 1 in our probability
distribution, and you do a
weighted sum of the values
to get your update.
So I have a query.
They have keys, dot products
to get interestingness or like
affinity, softmax to
normalize it, and then
weighted sum of those values
flow to me and update me.
And this is happening for
each node individually.
And then we update at the end.
And so this kind of a
message passing scheme
is at the heart of
the transformer.
And it happens in the more
vectorized batched way
that is more confusing and is
also interspersed with layer
norms and things like that
to make the training behave
better.
But that's roughly what's
happening in the attention
mechanism, I think,
on a high level.
So yeah, so in the communication
phase of the transformer, then
this message passing
scheme happens
in every head in parallel and
then in every layer in series
and with different
weights each time.
And that's it as far as the
multi-headed attention goes.
And so if you look at these
encooder-decoder models,
you can think of it then in
terms of the connectivity
of these nodes in the graph.
You can think of it as like,
OK, all these tokens that
are in the encoder that
we want to condition on,
they are fully
connected to each other.
So when they communicate,
they communicate fully
when you calculate
their features.
But in the decoder,
because we are
trying to have a
language model, we
don't want to have
communication for future tokens
because they give away
the answer at this step.
So the tokens in the
decoder are fully connected
from all the encoder
states, and then they
are also fully connected from
everything that is decoding.
And so you end up with
this triangular structure
in the data graph.
But that's the
message passing scheme
that this basically implements.
And then you have to be also
a little bit careful because
in the cross attention
here with the decoder,
you consume the features
from the top of the encoder.
So think of it as
in the encoder,
all the nodes are
looking at each other,
all the tokens are looking at
each other many, many times.
And they really figure
out what's in there,
and then the decoder when it's
looking only at the top nodes.
So that's roughly the
message passing scheme.
I was going to go into
more of an implementation
of a transformer.
I don't know if there's
any questions about this.
[INAUDIBLE] self-attention
and multi-headed attention,
but what is the
advantage of [INAUDIBLE]??
Yeah, so self-attention and
multi-headed attention, so
the multi-headed attention is
just this attention scheme,
but it's just applied
multiple times in parallel.
Multiple heads just means
independent applications
of the same attention.
So this message passing
scheme basically just
happens in parallel
multiple times
with different weights for
the query, key, and value.
So you can almost look at
it like in parallel, I'm
looking for, I'm seeking
different kinds of information
from different nodes.
And I'm collecting it
all in the same node.
It's all done in parallel.
So heads is really just
copy-paste in parallel.
And layers are
copy-paste but in series.
Maybe that makes sense.
And self-attention, when
it's self-attention,
what it's referring to
is that the node here
produces each node here.
So as I described it here,
this is really self-attention
because every one of
these nodes produces
a key query and a value
from this individual node.
When you have cross-attention,
you have one cross-attention
here, coming from the encoder.
That just means that
the queries are still
produced from this node,
but the keys and the values
are produced as a
function of nodes that
are coming from the encoder.
So I have my queries because
I'm trying to decode some--
the fifth word in the sequence.
And I'm looking
for certain things
because I'm the fifth word.
And then the keys and
the values in terms
of the source of information
that could answer my queries
can come from the previous
nodes in the current decoding
sequence or from the
top of the encoder.
So all the nodes that
have already seen all
of the encoding tokens many,
many times cannot broadcast
what they contain in
terms of information.
So I guess, to summarize,
the self-attention is--
sorry, cross-attention
and self-attention
only differ in where the piece
and the values come from.
Either the keys and values
are produced from this node,
or they are produced from some
external source like an encoder
and the nodes over there.
But algorithmically, is the
same mathematical operations.
Question.
Yeah, OK.
So two questions for you.
First question is, in the
message passing [INAUDIBLE]
So think of-- so each one
of these nodes is a token.
I guess they don't have
a very good picture of it
in the transformer.
But this node here could
represent the third word
in the output in the decoder,
and in the beginning,
it is just the
embedding of the word.
And then, OK, I have to
think through this analogy
a little bit more.
I came up with it this morning.
[LAUGHTER]
[INAUDIBLE]
What example of instantiation
[INAUDIBLE] nodes
as in in blocks were embedding?
These nodes are
basically the vectors.
I'll go to an implementation.
I'll go to the implementation,
and then maybe I'll
make the connections
to the graph.
So let me try to first
go to-- let me now go to,
with this intuition
in mind, at least,
to a nanoGPT, which is a
concrete implementation
of a transformer
that is very minimal.
So I worked on this
over the last few days,
and here it is reproducing
GPT-2 on open web text.
So it's a pretty serious
implementation that reproduces
GPT-2, I would say, and
provide it enough compute--
This was one node of 8 GPUs
for 38 hours or something
like that, if I
remember correctly.
And it's very readable.
It's 300 lines, so everyone
can take a look at it.
And yeah, let me basically
briefly step through it.
So let's try to have a
decoder-only transformer.
So what that means is that
it's a language model.
It tries to model the
next word in the sequence
or the next character
in the sequence.
So the data that
we train on this
is always some kind of text.
So here's some fake Shakespeare.
Sorry, this is real Shakespeare.
We're going to produce
fake Shakespeare.
So this is called
a Tiny Shakespeare
dataset, which is one of
my favorite toy datasets.
You take all of
Shakespeare, concatenate it,
and it's 1 megabyte
file, and then
you can train
language models on it
and get infinite
Shakespeare, if you like,
which I think is kind of cool.
So we have a text.
The first thing we
need to do is we
need to convert it to
a sequence of integers
because transformers
natively process--
you can't plug text
into transformer.
You need to somehow encode it.
So the way that
encoding is done is
we convert, for example,
in the simplest case,
every character gets an
integer, and then instead of "hi
there," we would have
this sequence of integers.
So then you can encode every
single character as an integer
and get a massive
sequence of integers.
You just concatenate
it all into one
large, long
one-dimensional sequence.
And then you can train on it.
Now, here, we only
have a single document.
In some cases, if you have
multiple independent documents,
what people like to do
is create special tokens,
and they intersperse
those documents
with those special
end of text tokens
that they splice in between
to create boundaries.
But those boundaries actually
don't have any modeling impact.
It's just that the
transformer is supposed
to learn via backpropagation
that the end of document
sequence means that you
should wipe the memory.
OK, so then we produce batches.
So these batches
of data just mean
that we go back to the
one-dimensional sequence,
and we take out chunks
of this sequence.
So say, if the block size is 8,
Then the block size indicates
the maximum length of context
that your transformer will
process.
So if our block size
is 8, that means
that we are going to have up
to eight characters of context
to predict the ninth
character in a sequence.
And the batch size indicates
how many sequences in parallel
we're going to process.
And we want this to be
as large as possible,
so we're fully taking
advantage of the GPU
and the parallels [INAUDIBLE]
So in this example,
we're doing a 4 by 8 batches.
So every row here is
independent example
and then every row here is a
small chunk of the sequence
that we're going to train on.
And then we have both the
inputs and the targets
at every single point here.
So to fully spell out what's
contained in a single 4
by 8 batch to the transformer--
I sort of compact it here--
so when the input is 47, by
itself, the target is 58.
And when the input is
the sequence 47, 58,
the target is one.
And when it's 47, 58, 1,
the target is 51 and so on.
So actually, the single batch
of examples that score by 8
actually has a ton of
individual examples
that we are expecting
a transformer
to learn on in parallel.
And so you'll see that
the batches are learned
on completely independently, but
the time dimension here along
horizontally is also
trained on in parallel.
So your real batch size
is more like B times T.
And it's just that the
context grows linearly
for the predictions that you
make along the T direction
in the model.
So this is all the examples
that the model will learn from,
this single batch.
So now, this is the GPT class.
And because this is
a decoder-only model,
so we're not going to have
an encoder because there's no
English we're translating from--
we're not trying to condition
in some other external
information.
We're just trying to produce
a sequence of words that
follow each other or likely to.
So this is all PyTorch, and
I'm going slightly faster
because I'm assuming people
have taken 231 or something
along those lines.
But here in the forward
pass, we take these indices,
and then we both encode the
identity of the indices,
just via an embedding
lookup table.
So every single integer, we
index into a lookup table of
vectors in this, and end
up embedding, and pull out
the word vector for that token.
And then because the
transformer by itself
doesn't actually-- the
process is set natively.
So we need to also positionally
encode these vectors
so that we basically
have both the information
about the token identity and
its place in the sequence from 1
to block size.
Now, the information
about what and where
is combined additively,
so the token embeddings
and the positional embeddings
are just added exactly as here.
So then there's
optional dropout,
this x here basically
just contains
the set of words
and their positions,
and that feeds into the
blocks of transformer.
And we're going to look
into what's block here.
But for here, for now,
this is just a series
of blocks in a transformer.
And then in the end,
there's a layer norm,
and then you're
decoding the logits
for the next word or next
integer in a sequence,
using the linear projection of
the output of this transformer
So LM head here, a short
core language model head.
It's just a linear function.
So basically, positionally
encode all the words,
feed them into a
sequence of blocks,
and then apply a linear
layer to get the probability
distribution for
the next character.
And then if we have
the targets, which
we produced in the data order--
and you'll notice that
the targets are just
the inputs offset
by one in time--
then those targets feed
into a cross entropy loss.
So this is just a
negative log likelihood
typical classification loss.
So now let's drill into
what's here in the blocks.
So these blocks that are
applied sequentially,
there's, again, as I
mentioned, this communicate
phase and the compute phase.
So in the communicate
phase, all the nodes
get to talk to each other, and
so these nodes are basically,
if our block size
is 8, then we are
going to have eight
nodes in this graph.
There's eight nodes
in this graph.
The first node is pointed
to only by itself.
The second node is pointed to
by the first node and itself.
The third node is pointed
to by the first two nodes
and itself, et cetera.
So there's eight nodes here.
So you apply-- there's a
residual pathway and x.
You take it out.
You apply a layer norm,
and then the self-attention
so that these communicate,
these eight nodes communicate.
But you have to keep in
mind that the batch is 4.
So because batch is 4,
this is also applied--
so we have eight
nodes communicating,
but there's a batch of four of
them individually communicating
in one of those eight nodes.
There's no crisscross across
the batch dimension, of course.
There's no batch
anywhere luckily.
And then once they've
changed information,
they are processed using
the multi-layer perceptron.
And that's the compute phase.
And then also here we are
missing the cross-attention
because this is a
decoder-only model.
So all we have is
this step here,
the multi-headed
attention, and that's
this line, the
communicate phase.
And then we have the feed
forward, which is the MLP,
and that's the compute phase.
I'll take question's
a bit later.
Then the MLP here is
fairly straightforward.
The MLP is just individual
processing on each node,
just transforming the feature
representation at that node.
So applying a
two-layer neural net
with a GELU nonlinearity,
which is just
think of it as a ReLU
or something like that.
It's just a nonlinearity.
And then MLP is straightforward.
I don't think there's
anything too crazy there.
And then this is the
causal self-attention part,
the communication phase.
So this is like
the meat of things
and the most complicated part.
It's only complicated
because of the batching
and the implementation detail
of how you mask the connectivity
in the graph so that
you can't obtain
any information
from the future when
you're predicting your token.
Otherwise, it gives
away the information.
So if I'm the fifth token and
if I'm the fifth position,
then I'm getting the fourth
token coming into the input,
and I'm attending to the
third, second, and first,
and I'm trying to figure
out what is the next token.
Well then, in this batch,
in the next element
over in the time dimension,
the answer is at the input.
So I can't get any
information from there.
So that's why this
is all tricky,
but basically, in
the forward pass,
we are calculating the queries,
keys, and values based on x.
So these are the keys,
queries, and values.
Here, when I'm
computing the attention,
I have the queries matrix
multiplying the piece.
So this is the dot product in
parallel for all the queries
and all the keys
in all the heads.
So I failed to mention
that there's also
the aspect of the heads, which
is also done all in parallel
here.
So we have the batch
dimension, the time dimension,
and the head dimension,
and you end up
with five-dimensional tensors,
and it's all really confusing.
So I invite you to step through
it later and convince yourself
that this is actually
doing the right thing.
But basically, you have the
batch dimension, the head
dimension and the
time dimension,
and then you have
features at them.
And so this is evaluating for
all the batch elements, for all
the head elements, and
all the time elements,
the simple Python that I gave
you earlier, which is query
dot product p.
Then here, we do a masked_fill,
and what this is doing
is it's basically clamping the
attention between the nodes
that are not supposed to
communicate to be negative
infinity.
And we're doing
negative infinity
because we're about to softmax,
and so negative infinity will
make basically the attention
that those elements be zero.
And so here we are going
to basically end up
with the weights, the affinities
between these nodes, optional
dropout.
And then here, attention
matrix multiply v is basically
the gathering of the information
according to the affinities
we calculated.
And this is just a
weighted sum of the values
at all those nodes.
So this matrix multiplies
is doing that weighted sum.
And then transpose
contiguous view
because it's all
complicated and batched
in five-dimensional
tensors, but it's really not
doing anything,
optional drop out,
and then a linear projection
back to the residual pathway.
So this is implementing the
communication phase here.
Then you can train
this transformer.
And then you can generate
infinite Shakespeare.
And you will simply do this by--
because our block size is 8,
we start with a sum token,
say like, I used
in this case, you
can use something like a
new line as the start token.
And then you communicate
only to yourself
because there's a
single node, and you
get the probability
distribution for the first word
in the sequence.
And then you decode it
for the first character
in the sequence.
You decode the character.
And then you bring
back the character,
and you re-encode
it as an integer.
And now, you have
the second thing.
And so you get--
OK, we're at the first
position, and this
is whatever integer it is,
add the positional encodings,
goes into the sequence,
goes in the transformer,
and again, this token
now communicates
with the first token
and it's identity.
And so you just keep
plugging it back.
And once you run out of the
block size, which is eight,
you start to crawl,
because you can never
have watt size more than
eight in the way you've
trained this transformer.
So we have more and more
context until eight.
And then if you want to
generate beyond eight,
you have to start cropping
because the transformer only
works for eight elements
in time dimension.
And so all of these transformers
in the [INAUDIBLE] setting
have a finite block
size or context length,
and in typical models, this
will be 1,024 tokens or 2,048
tokens, something like that.
But these tokens are
usually like BPE tokens,
or SentencePiece tokens,
or WorkPiece tokens.
There's many
different encodings.
So it's not like that long.
And so that's why, I
think, [INAUDIBLE]..
We really want to
expand the context size,
and it gets gnarly
because the attention
is sporadic in the
[INAUDIBLE] case.
Now, if you want to implement
an encoder instead of a decoder
attention.
Then all you have to
do is this [INAUDIBLE]
and you just delete that line.
So if you don't
mask the attention,
then all the nodes
communicate to each other,
and everything is
allowed, and information
flows between all the nodes.
So if you want to have the
encoder here, just delete.
All the encoder blocks
will use attention
where this line is deleted.
That's it.
So you're allowing whatever--
this encoder might store say,
10 tokens, 10 nodes,
and they are all
allowed to communicate to each
other going up the transformer.
And then if you want to
implement cross-attention,
so you have a full
encoder-decoder transformer,
not just a decoder-only
transformer or a GPT.
Then we need to also add
cross-attention in the middle.
So here, there is a
self-attention piece where all
the--
there's a self-attention
piece, a cross-attention piece,
and this MLP.
And in the
cross-attention, we need
to take the features from
the top of the encoder.
We need to add one
more line here,
and this would be the
cross-attention instead of a--
I should have implemented
it instead of just pointing,
I think.
But there will be a
cross-attention line here.
So we'll have three
lines because we
need to add another block.
And the queries will
come from x but the keys
and the values will come
from the top of the encoder.
And there will be
basic code information
flowing from the
encoder, strictly
to all the nodes inside x.
And then that's it.
So it's a very
simple modifications
on the decoder attention.
So you'll hear people
talk that you have
a decoder-only model like GPT.
You can have an encoder-only
model like BERT,
or you can have an
encoder-decoder model
like say T5, doing things
like machine translation.
And in BERT, you can't train
it using this language modeling
setup that's utter
aggressive, and you're just
trying to predict next
[INAUDIBLE] in the sequence.
You're training it doing
slightly different objectives.
You're putting in
the full sentence,
and, the full sentence is
allowed to communicate fully.
And then you're trying to
classify sentiment or something
like that.
So you're not trying to model
the next token in the sequence.
So these are trained
slightly different
using masking and other
denoising techniques.
OK.
So that's like the transformer.
I'm going to continue.
So yeah, maybe more questions.
[INAUDIBLE]
This is like we are enforcing
these constraints on it
by just masking [INAUDIBLE]
So I'm not sure
if I fully follow.
So there's different ways
to look at this analogy,
but one analogy is
you can interpret
this graph as really fixed.
It's just that every time
we do the communicate,
we are using different weights.
You can look at it that way.
So if we have block size
of eight in my example,
we would have eight nodes.
Here we have 2, 4, 6.
OK, so we'd have eight nodes.
They would be connected in--
you lay them out, and you only
connect from left to right.
[INAUDIBLE]
Why would they
connect-- usually,
the connections don't change
as a function of the data
or something like that--
[INAUDIBLE]
I don't think I've seen
a single example where
the connectivity
changes dynamically
in the function data.
Usually, the
connectivity is fixed.
If you have an encoder,
and you're training a BERT,
you have how many
tokens you want,
and they are fully connected.
And if you have a
decoder-only model,
you have this triangular
thing, and if you
have encoder-decoder,
then you have
awkwardly two pools of nodes.
Yeah.
Go ahead.
[INAUDIBLE] I wonder, you
know much more about this
than I know.
But do you have a sense of
like if you ran [INAUDIBLE]
In my head, I'm thinking
[INAUDIBLE] but then you also
have different things for
one or more of [INAUDIBLE]----
Yeah, it's really
hard to say, so that's
why I think this paper is so
interesting because like, yeah,
usually, you'd
see like the path,
and maybe they had
path internally.
They just didn't publish it.
All you can see is things that
didn't look like a transformer.
I mean, you have ResNets,
which have lots of this.
But a ResNet would be
like this, but there's
no self-attention component.
But the MLP is there
kind of in a ResNet.
So a ResNet looks
very much like this
except there's no-- you can
use layer norms in ResNets,
I believe, as well.
Typically, sometimes,
they can be batch norms.
So it is kind of like a ResNet.
It is like they took
a ResNet, and they
put in a self-attention
block in addition
to the preexisting
MLP block, which
is kind of like convolutions.
And MLP was strictly
speaking deconvolution,
one by one convolution,
but I think
the idea is similar in that MLP
is just like a typical weights,
nonlinearity weights operation.
But I will say, yeah, this
is kind of interesting
because a lot of
work is not there,
and then they give
you this transformer.
And then it turns
out 5 years later,
it's not changed, even though
everyone's trying to change it.
So it's interesting to me
that it's like a package,
in like a package,
which I think is really
interesting historically.
And I also talked
to paper authors,
and they were
unaware of the impact
that the transformer
would have at the time.
So when you read this paper,
actually, it's unfortunate
because this is the paper
that changed everything,
but when people read it,
it's like question marks
because it reads like a pretty
random machine translation
paper.
It's like, oh, we're
doing machine translation.
Oh, here's a cool architecture.
OK, great, good results.
It doesn't know what's
going to happen.
[LAUGHS] And so when
people read it today,
I think they're
confused potentially.
I will have some
tweets at the end,
but I think I would
have renamed it
with the benefit of hindsight
of like, well, I'll get to it.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, I think that's a
good question as well.
Currently, I mean,
I certainly don't
love the autoregressive
modeling approach.
I think it's kind of
weird to sample a token
and then commit to it.
So maybe there are
some ways, some hybrids
with the Fusion as
an example, which
I think would be
really cool, or we'll
find some other ways to edit
the sequences later but still
in our regressive framework.
But I think the Fusion is
like an up and coming modeling
approach that I personally
find much more appealing.
When I sample text, I don't
go chunk, chunk, chunk,
and commit.
I do a draft one, and then
I do a better draft two.
And that feels like
a diffusion process.
So that would be my hope.
OK, also a question.
So yeah, you'd think
the [INAUDIBLE]
And then once we
have the edge rates,
we just have to multiply
it by the values,
and then you just
[INAUDIBLE] it.
Yes, yeah, it's right.
And you think there's MLG
within graph neural networks
and they'll potentially--
I find the graph neural
networks like a confusing term
because, I mean,
yeah, previously,
there, was this notion of--
I feel like maybe today
everything is a graph neural
network because a transformer
is a graph neural network
processor.
The native representation that
the transformer operates over
is sets that are connected
by edges in a direct way.
And so that's the native
representation, and then, yeah.
OK, I should go on because
I still have 30 slides.
[INAUDIBLE]
Oh yeah, yeah, the root
DE, I think, it basically
like if you're initializing
with random weights
setup from a [INAUDIBLE] as
your dimension size grows,
so does your values,
the variance grows.
And then your softmax will just
become the one half vector.
So it's just a way to
control the variance
and bring it to always be
in a good range for softmax
and nice diffused distribution.
OK, so it's almost like
an initialization thing.
OK, so transformers
have been applied
to all the other fields,
and the way this was done
is in my opinion,
ridiculous ways
honestly because I was a
computer vision person,
and you have ComNets,
and they make sense.
So what we're doing now
with VITs as an example is
you take an image and you chop
it up into little squares.
And then those
squares, literally,
feed into a
transformer, and that's
it, which is kind of ridiculous.
And so, I mean, yeah,
and so the transformer
doesn't even, in the simplest
case, really know where
these patches might come from.
They are usually
positionally encoded,
but it has to rediscover
a lot of the structure,
I think, of them in some ways.
And it's kind of weird
to approach it that way.
But it's just the
simplest baseline
of just chomping up big
images into small squares
and feeding them in as the
individual nodes actually
works fairly well.
And then this is in a
transformer encoder,
so all the patches are
talking to each other
throughout the
entire transformer.
And the number of nodes
here would be like nine.
Also, in speech recognition, you
just take your melSpectrogram,
and you chop it up into
slices and you feed them
into a transformer.
So there was paper like
this, but also Whisper.
Whisper is a
copy-paste transformer.
If you saw Whisper from OpenAI,
you just chop up melSpectrogram
and feed it into a
transformer and then pretend
you're dealing with text.
And it works very well.
Decision transformer in RL,
you take your states, actions,
and reward that you
experience in environment,
and you just pretend
it's a language.
Then you start to model
the sequences of that,
and then you can use
that for planning later.
That works really well.
Even things AlphaFold,
so we were briefly
talking about molecules and
how you can plug them in.
So at the heart of
AlphaFold, computationally,
is also a transformer.
One thing I wanted to also
say about transformers
is I find that
they're very flexible,
and I really enjoy that.
I'll give you an
example from Tesla.
You have a ComNet
that takes an image
and makes predictions
about the image.
And then the big
question is, how do you
feed in extra information?
And it's not always
trivial like say, I
had additional
information that I
want to inform that I want
the outputs to be informed by.
Maybe I have other
sensors like Radar.
Maybe I have some map
information, or a vehicle type,
or some audio.
And the question is, how do you
feed information into a ComNet?
Like where do you feed it in?
Do you concatenate it?
Do you add it?
At what stage?
And so with a transformer,
it's much easier
because you just take
whatever you want, you chop it
up into pieces, and you
feed it in with a set
of what you had before.
And you let the
self-attention figure out
how everything
should communicate.
And that actually
apparently works.
So just chop up everything
and throw it into the mix
is like the way.
And it frees neural
nets from this burgeon
of Euclidean space,
where previously you
had to arrange your computation
to conform to the Euclidean
space or three dimensions of how
you're laying out the compute.
Like the compute
actually kind of
happens in almost like 3D
space if you think about it.
But in attention,
everything is just sets.
So it's a very
flexible framework,
and you can just throw in stuff
into your conditioning set.
And everything just
self-attended over.
So it's quite beautiful
from that perspective.
OK, so now what exactly makes
transformers so effective?
I think a good
example of this comes
from the GPT-3 paper, which
I encourage people to read.
Language Models of
Few-Shot Learners.
I would have probably
renamed this a little bit.
I would have said
something like transformers
are capable of in-context
learning or meta-learning.
That's like what makes
them really special.
So basically the setting
that they're working with
is, OK, I have some
context, and I'm
trying-- like say, a passage.
This is just one
example of many.
I have a passage, and I'm
asking questions about it.
And then as part of the
context in the prompt,
I'm giving the questions
and the answers.
So I'm giving one example
of question-answer,
another example of
question-answer,
question-answer, and so on.
And this becomes--
Oh yeah, people are going
to have to leave soon, huh?
OK, is this really important?
Let me think.
OK, so what's really
interesting is basically
like with more examples
given in a context,
the accuracy improves.
And so what that can set
is that the transformer
is able to somehow
learn in the activations
without doing any
gradient descent
in a typical
fine-tuning fashion.
So if you fine-tune, you have to
give an example and the answer,
and you fine-tune it,
using gradient descent.
But it looks like the
transformer internally
in its weights is
doing something
that looks like potentially
gradient, some kind
of a metalearning in the
weights of the transformer
as it is reading the prompt.
And so in this paper,
they go into, OK,
distinguishing this outer
loop with stochastic gradient
descent in this inner loop
of the intercontext learning.
So the inner loop is as
the transformer is reading
the sequence almost and the
outer loop is the training
by gradient descent.
So basically,
there's some training
happening in the activations
of the transformer
as it is consuming
a sequence that
may be very much looks
like gradient descent.
And so there are some recent
papers that hint at this
and study it.
And so as an example,
in this paper
here, they propose something
called the draw operator.
And they argue that the
raw operator is implemented
by transformer,
and then they show
that you can implement
things like ridge regression
on top of the raw operator.
And so this is giving--
There are papers
hinting that maybe there
is some thing that looks
like gradient-based learning
inside the activations
of the transformer.
And I think this is not
impossible to think through
because what is
gradient-based learning?
Overpass, backward
pass, and then update.
Oh, that looks like
a ResNet, right,
because you're adding
to the weights.
So the start of initial
random set of weights,
forward pass, backward pass,
and update your weights,
and then forward pass, backward
pass, update the weights.
Looks like a ResNet.
Transformer is a ResNet,
so much more hand-wavey,
but basically, some
papers are trying
to hint at why that would
be potentially possible.
And then I have a bunch of
tweets I just copy-pasted here
in the end.
This was like meant for
general consumption,
so they're a bit more high-level
and hypey a little bit.
But I'm talking about why this
architecture is so interesting
and why potentially
it became so popular.
And I think it
simultaneously optimizes
three properties that, I
think, are very desirable.
Number one, the
transformer is very
expressive in the forward pass.
It sort of like it's
able to implement
very interesting functions,
potentially functions
that can even do meta-learning.
Number two, it is very
optimizable thanks
to things like residual
connections, layer nodes,
and so on.
And number three, it's
extremely efficient.
This is not always appreciated,
but the transformer,
if you look at the
computational graph,
is a shallow, wide
network, which
is perfect to take advantage
of the parallelism of GPUs.
So I think the transformer
was designed very deliberately
to run efficiently on GPUs.
There's previous
work like neural GPU
that I really enjoy as
well, which is really just
like how do we design neural
nets that are efficient on GPUs
and thinking backwards from the
constraints of the hardware,
which I think is a
very interesting way
to think about it.
Oh yeah, so here, I'm saying,
I probably would have called--
I probably would've called the
transformer a general purpose
efficient optimizable
computer instead of attention
is all you need.
That's what I would have maybe
in hindsight called that paper.
It's proposing a model that
is very general purpose, so
forward passes, expressive.
It's very efficient
in terms of GPU usage
and is easily optimizable by
gradient descent and trains
very nicely.
And then I have some
other hype tweets here.
Anyway, so you can
read them later.
But I think this one
is maybe interesting.
So if previous neural nets
are special purpose computers
designed for a
specific task, GPT
is a general purpose computer,
reconfigurable at runtime
to run natural
language programs.
So the programs are
given as prompts,
and then GPT runs the program
by completing the document.
So I really like these analogies
personally to computer.
It's just like a
powerful computer,
and it's optimizable
by gradient descent.
And I don't know--
OK, yeah.
That's it.
[LAUGHTER]
You can read the tweets
later, but that's for now.
I'll just thank you.
I'll just leave this up.
Sorry, I just found this tweet.
So turns out that if you
scale up the training set
and use a powerful enough
neural net like a transformer,
the network becomes a
kind of general purpose
computer over text.
So I think that's nice
way to look at it.
And instead of performing
a single text sequence,
you can design the
sequence in the prompt.
And because the transformer
is both powerful
but also is trained on large
enough, very hard data set,
it becomes this general
purpose text computer.
And so I think that's kind of
interesting way to look at it.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
And I guess my question
is [INAUDIBLE] how
much do you think [INAUDIBLE]?
really because it's mostly
more efficient or [INAUDIBLE]
So I think there's
a bit of that.
Yeah, so I would say
RNNs in principle,
yes, they can implement
arbitrary programs.
I think, it's like a useless
statement to some extent
because they're probably--
I'm not sure that they're
probably expressive
because in a sense of power
and that they can implement
these arbitrary functions.
But they're not optimizable.
And they're certainly not
efficient because they
are serial computing devices.
So if you look at it
as a compute graph,
RNNs are very long,
thin compute graph.
What if you stretched out
the neurons and you looked--
like take all the individual
neurons interconnectivity,
and stretch them out, and
try to visualize them.
RNNs would be like a very
long graph and that's bad.
And it's bad also
for optimizability
because I don't
exactly know why,
but just the rough intuition
is when you're backpropagating,
you don't want to
make too many steps.
And so transformers are a
shallow wide graph, and so
from supervision to inputs is
a very small number of hops.
And it's a long
residual pathways,
which make gradients
flow very easily.
And there's all
these layer norms
to control the scales of
all of those activations.
And so there's
not too many hops,
and you're going from
supervision to input
very quickly and just
flows through the graph.
And it can all be
done in parallel,
so you don't need to do this--
encoder and decoder RNNs, you
have to go from first word,
then second word,
then third word.
But here in transformer,
every single word
was processed completely in
parallel, which is kind of a--
So I think all of these are
really important because all
of these are really important.
And I think number 3 is less
talked about but extremely
important because in deep
learning scale matters.
And so the size of the
network that you can train it
gives you is
extremely important.
And so if it's efficient
on the current hardware,
then you can make it bigger.
You mentioned that if you do
it with multiple modalities
of data, [INAUDIBLE].
How does that actually work?
Do you leave the different
data as different token,
or is it [INAUDIBLE]?
No, so yeah, so you
take your image,
and you apparently chop
them up into patches.
So there's the first
thousand tokens or whatever.
And now, I have a special--
so radar could be also,
but I don't actually
want to make a
representation of radar.
But you just need to
chop it up and enter it.
And then you have to
encode it somehow.
Like the transformer
needs to know
that they're coming from radar.
So you create a special--
you have some kind of a
special token of that to--
these radar tokens
are what's slightly
different in the
representation, and it's
learnable by gradient descent.
And like vehicle
information would also
come in with a special embedded
token that can be learned.
So--
So how do you line
those before really--
Actually, but you don't.
It's all just a set.
And there's--
Even the [INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, it's all just a set,
but you can positionally
encode these sets if you want.
So positional
encoding means you can
hardwire, for example,
the coordinates
like using [INAUDIBLE].
You can hardwire
that, but it's better
if you don't hardwire
the position.
It's just a vector
that is always
hanging out the dislocation.
Whatever content is
there, it just adds on it.
And this vector is
trainable by background.
That's how you do it.
Good point.
I don't really like
the [INAUDIBLE]..
They seem to work, but it
seems like they're sometimes
[INAUDIBLE]
I'm not sure if I
understand your question.
[LAUGHTER]
So I mean the
positional encoders
like they're actually like not--
OK, so they have very little
inductive bias or something
like that.
They're just vectors hanging
out in location always,
and you're trying to help
the network in some way.
And I think the
intuition is good,
but if you have
enough data, usually,
trying to mess with
it is a bad thing.
Trying to enter
knowledge when you
have enough
knowledge in the data
set itself is not
usually productive.
So it all really depends
on what scale you want.
If you have infinity
data, then you actually
want to encode less and less.
That turns out to work better.
And if you have very little
data, then actually, you do
want to encode some biases.
And maybe if you have a
much smaller data set, then
maybe convolutions
are a good idea
because you actually have this
bias coming from your filters.
But I think-- so the transformer
is extremely general,
but there are ways to
mess with the encodings
to put in more structure.
Like you could, for example,
encode [INAUDIBLE] and fix it,
or you could actually go
to the attention mechanism
and say, OK, if my image
is chopped up into patches,
this patch can only communicate
to this neighborhood.
And you just do that in
the attention matrix,
you just mask out whatever
you don't want to communicate.
And so people really
play with this
because the full
attention is inefficient.
So they will intersperse,
for example, layers
that only communicate
in little patches
and then layers that
communicate globally.
And they will do all
kinds of tricks like that.
So you can slowly bring
in more inductive bias.
You would do it, but
the inductive biases
are like they're factored out
from the core transformer.
And they are factored out,
and the interconnectivity
of the nodes.
And they are factored
out in the positionally--
and you can mess with
this for computation.
[INAUDIBLE]
So there's probably about 200
papers on this now if not more.
They're kind of hard
to keep track of.
Honestly, like my Safari
browser, which is-- oh,
it's all up on my computer,
like 200 open tabs.
But yes, I'm not
even sure if I want
to pick my favorite honestly.
Yeah, [INAUDIBLE]
Maybe you can use a transformer
like that [INAUDIBLE]
The other one that I
actually like even more
is potentially, keep
the context length fixed
but allow the network to
somehow use a scratch pad.
And so the way this works is
you will teach the transformer
somehow via examples
in [INAUDIBLE] hey,
you actually have a scratch pad.
Basically, you can't
remember too much.
Your context line is finite.
But you can use a scratch pad.
And you do that by emitting
a start scratch pad,
and then writing whatever you
want to remember, and then
end scratch pad.
And then you continue
with whatever you want.
And then later
when it's decoding,
you actually have
special objects
that when you detect
start scratch pad,
you will like save
whatever it puts
in there in like external thing
and allow it to attend over it.
So basically, you can teach the
transformer just dynamically
because it's so meta-learned.
You can teach it dynamically
to use other gizmos and gadgets
and allow it to expand
its memory that way
if that makes sense.
It's just like human learning
to use a notepad, right.
You don't have to
keep it in your brain.
So keeping things in your
brain is like the context line
from the transformer.
But maybe we can just
give it a notebook.
And then it can query the
notebook, and read from it,
and write to it.
[INAUDIBLE] transformer to
plug in another transformer.
[LAUGHTER]
[INAUDIBLE]
I don't know if I detected that.
I feel like-- did you feel
like there was more than just
a long prompt that's unfolding?
Yeah, [INAUDIBLE]
I didn't try extensively, but
I did see a [INAUDIBLE] event.
And I felt like the block
size was just moved.
Maybe I'm wrong.
I don't actually know about
the internals of ChatGPT.
We have two online questions.
So one question is, "what do
you think about architecture
[INAUDIBLE]?"
S4?
S4.
I'm sorry.
I don't know S4.
Which one is this one?
The second question, this
one's a personal question.
"What are you going
to work on next?"
[INAUDIBLE]
I mean, so right now, I'm
working on things like nanoGPT.
Where is nanoGPT?
I mean, I'm going basically
slightly from computer vision
and like computer
vision-based products, do
a little bit in language domain.
Where's ChatGPT?
OK, nanoGPT.
So originally, I had minGPT,
which I rewrote to nanoGPT.
And I'm working on this.
I'm trying to reproduce
GPTs, and I mean,
I think something
like ChatGPT, I think,
incrementally improved
in a product fashion
would be extremely interesting.
And I think a lot
of people feel it,
and that's why it went so wide.
So I think there's
something like a Google plus
plus plus to build that I
think is more interesting.
Shall we give our speaker
a round of applause?